<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-05-06T21:36:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Riviera Sperduto - Developer Portfolio</title><subtitle>Portfolio of Riviera Sperduto - Full Stack Developer, Cloud/Solutions Architect, and AI Developer. Showcasing projects, skills, and services.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Welcome to My Portfolio Website</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/05/05/welcome-to-my-portfolio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to My Portfolio Website" /><published>2025-05-05T10:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-05-05T10:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/05/05/welcome-to-my-portfolio</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/05/05/welcome-to-my-portfolio/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;hello-and-welcome&quot;&gt;Hello and Welcome!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for visiting my portfolio website. This is my first official blog post, marking the launch of this site where I’ll be documenting my professional journey and sharing knowledge about software development, cloud architecture, and artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-to-expect&quot;&gt;What to Expect&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this blog, you can expect to find:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project Showcases&lt;/strong&gt;: Detailed walkthroughs of my projects, highlighting the technologies used, challenges faced, and solutions implemented.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technical Tutorials&lt;/strong&gt;: Step-by-step guides on various technologies and programming concepts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cloud Architecture&lt;/strong&gt;: Insights and best practices in designing scalable and reliable cloud solutions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AI Development&lt;/strong&gt;: Explorations into artificial intelligence, machine learning concepts, and practical applications.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Career Insights&lt;/strong&gt;: Reflections on my professional journey and lessons learned along the way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stay-connected&quot;&gt;Stay Connected&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to share my knowledge and experiences with you. Feel free to explore my portfolio, check out my projects, and connect with me on LinkedIn or through the contact page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog will be regularly updated with new content, so make sure to subscribe to the newsletter to stay informed about the latest posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to this journey together!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Riviera Sperduto</name></author><category term="development" /><category term="welcome" /><category term="portfolio" /><category term="software-development" /><summary type="html">Welcome to my portfolio website where I&apos;ll be sharing my journey, projects, and insights about software development, cloud architecture, and AI.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/blog-social-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/blog-social-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>